Helen Johnson Martin Papers MS260
Tufts Archival Research Center
Helen Johnson Martin Papers
1943 -- 1947
circa 1940s - 1990s
Tufts Archival Research Center
Martin, Helen Johnson, 1925-2016
MS260
1 Linear Feet
This collection contains collected or created by Helen Johnson Martin and pertaining to her time as a student in the Jackson College for Women at Tufts College from 1943-1947.
Scope and Contents
The materials within this collection are related to the life of Helen Johnson Martin and her friends during their time as undergraduate students at Tufts College from 1943-1947. The collection includes photographs, documents, articles on John Holmes, poetry, books, graded writing assignments completed by Martin, a Tuftonian medallion, materials relating to the class of 1947 50th class reunion, the 1947 Jumbo yearbook, and a scrapbook.
The scrapbook depicts her life as a student on campus with her friends, small drawings, student organization materials, rulebooks for living in the dorms, programs for various events on campus, writing projects, poems, and news articles about World War II. The scrapbook contains newspaper clippings, photographs of Martin and her friends, poems, artwork, letters, cards, advertisements, rules for the female dormitories, and more.
Martin took several classes with famed Tufts poet and professor John Holmes and collected a number of materials by him, including handwritten poems and copies of the books Map of My Country (signed) and The Poet's Work.
Biographical / Historical
Helen Eva Johnson Martin was born to Edith Hoesktra and Robert Johnson in North Middleboro, Massachusetts on May 21, 1925. She attended Wakefield High School and enrolled in Tufts College as a student at the Jackson College for Women in 1943. Martin took courses and participated in seminars lead by Professor John Holmes throughout her career at Tufts. As a student Martin attended Tufts on a full scholarship and also worked as a nanny for members of the Tufts community and families in New York City. Martin served as the managing editor and the co-editor in chief of the Tuftonian for the 1946-1947 school year, and was the feature editor (Jackson) of the 1947 Jumbo yearbook. In addition to work on the Tuftonian and the Jumbo, Martin was an active member of the Canterbury Club, the Sociology Club, the Alexander Bain Society, Student Council, and served as house president of her dorm. Martin graduated from Tufts in 1947 with a Bachelor of Science in Psychology.
After graduating, Martin began working for the University of Northern Colorado, where she met Albert Martin, whom she married in 1949. They settled in Pasadena, California and raised two children, daughter Laurel and son Tracy. In 1963 Martin received a Master's in Vocational Counseling from the California State College in Los Angeles, and later worked for the State of California's Department of Rehabilitation, becoming the Assistant Deputy Director for Field Operations for Southern California. She relocated to Sacramento, California and worked in the Department of Rehabilitation for 30 years. Helen Johnson Martin died in Tempe, Arizona in 2016 at the age of 91.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection are organized in received order.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Laurel Martin, daughter of Helen E. Johnson Martin, on October 15, 2020, accession number MS-2021-026.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Related Materials
John A. Holmes Papers, 1813 -- 1998. Tufts University. Digital Collections and Archives. Medford, MA.
Alumni collections; Alumni and alumnae; Student life; Curriculum and Instruction -- Student Work; Holmes, John; Martin, Helen Johnson, 1925-2016
- "Along the Row" and "Spring" by John Holmes manuscript and typescript, 1946 -- 1947; MS260.000001; Gittleman, Sol, 1934-; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  Civil War
- Helen Johnson Martin photograph, 1947; MS260.000002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 2)
- John Holmes clippings and related correspondence, circa 1990; MS260.000003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Class of 1947 50th reunion correspondence, 1997; MS260.000004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 4)
- School work and Tufts records, circa 1943 -- 1947; MS260.000005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Alumni magazines, 1945 -- 1962; MS260.000014 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Helen Johnson Martin photos and documents, 1938 -- 1993; MS260.000015; 3 Digital Object(s) 3 digital objects comprising 58 files.; 193 Megabytes
  Scope and Contents
  Original disk annotation: "Helen Johnson Martin BS 1947 Tufts compilation of photos and docs digitized by Laurel Martin 2020"
  - Diplomas, certificates, biography, and photos, 1938 -- 1993; MS260.000016; 1 Digital Object(s) 1 digital object comprising 12 files.; 15 Megabytes
  - Tufts era photo album, 1943 -- 1947; MS260.000017; 1 Digital Object(s) 1 digital object comprising 37 files.; 177 Megabytes
  - Tufts photos, 1943 -- 1947; MS260.000018; 1 Digital Object(s) 1 digital object comprising 9 files.; 11 Megabytes
- Along the Row at Tufts College by John Holmes, 1944; MS260.000007; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Tuftonian medallion, circa 1943 -- 1947; MS260.000008; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 9)
- The Poet's Work by John Holmes, 1939; MS260.000009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Map of My Country by John Holmes, 1943; MS260.000010; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 11)
- 1947 Jumbo yearbook, MS260.000011; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Diploma, 1947; MS260.000012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Scrapbook, circa 1940 -- 1947; MS260.000013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Content Warning
  This scrapbook contains a poem describing potential sexual violence in a supposedly humorous tone. For more information on DCA's content warning policy please visit our website: https://dca.tufts.edu/content-warnings-protocal-for-digital-archival-material